+92 309 6293789Lahore, Pakistanabbas.qaixer@gmail.com

Qaiser Abbas MLEngineer | Data Scientist

☐ github/qaixerabbas ☐ linkedin/qaixerabbas ⓒ qaixerabbas.github.io

Experienced Machine Learning Engineer with 4+ years of industrial experience. Skilled in Deep Learning, Computer Vision, Natural Language Processing, and Data Science. Strong R&D professional currently working as a Sr. MLE at SDSol Technologies

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages Python, C++, MATLAB (Basic), JS (Basic), SQL

Deep Learning Keras, TensorFlow, OpenCV, FastAl, PyTorch, OpenVino, Transformers, SpaCy, NLTK

Machine Learning Numpy, Pandas, scikit-learn, Matplotlib, Seaborn

Tools Linux, VS Code, Jupyter-Notebook, Google Colab, Postman, Streamlit

Technologies Git, FastAPI, HTML, CSS, Docker, Azure, AWS

Soft Skills Time Management, Leadership, Communication, Team Work

EXPERIENCE

Sr. Machine Learning Engineer

Nov 2022 — Present

SDSol Technologies

Lahore, Pakistan

- Designed and Developed an Audio Analysis Pipeline for Psychological Applications using LLMs (Whisper and GPT)
- Developed a Multiprocessing GPU based pipeline for audio (therapy sessions) processing.
- Utilized LLMs (GPTs) for development of a personalized treatment plan generation for mental health.
- Finetuned GPT 3.5 Turbo for custom treatment plan generation using OpenAI Python SDK and deployed using FastAPI on AWS EC2.
- Trained small language models (BERT, ALBERT) for customer query classification for reducing OpenAI API costs.
- · Leveraged LangChain and LlamaIndex for custom document question answering bot.
- Developed a website assistant bot using GPT and LlamaIndex and deployed using FastAPI.
- Developed a tennis player/ball detection model via finetuning YOLOv8 and integrated it into active learning pipeline for automatic annotation using LabelStudio.
- · Utilized deep transfer learning for development of aerial scene understanding models using remote sensing images.
- Developed a human related crime identification model via finetuning EfficientNet and trained on custom dataset.
- Leveraged AWS services including EC2, S3, Lambda, ECR, and AppRunner to ensure seamless and scalable system deployment.
- Pioneered the development of a GPU-accelerated backend daemon on EC2 for audio and text data processing.
- Utilized unsupervised association rule mining to craft a personalized food recommendation system and implemented it as a robust REST API using FastAPI.
- Developed an insect classification model using Transfer Learning, optimized for CPU inference using Intel OpenVino and deployed using ACR and Azure App service.

Software Engineer (Deep Learning & Computer Vision)

Nov 2021 — Jan 2022

Wortel AI

Remote

- Created a robust weed detection algorithm using YOLOv5 and satellite imagery.
- Developed a medical speech recognition system by fine-tuning an Nvidia QuartNet model via NeMo library.
- Leveraged AWS S3 and MLFlow platforms for efficient deployment and continuous maintenance of deep learning models.

AI Instructor & Teaching Fellow

Mar 2021 — Sep 2022

Lahore

University of Engineering and Technology Lahore

- Effectively taught comprehensive undergraduate courses in both AI & ML, including theory and hands-on lab sessions.
- Collaborated closely with senior faculty members for development of AI/ML course content & preparation of research grant proposals.
- Authored a research proposal titled "Tea Disease Detection using Machine Learning and Remote Sensing." which achieved notable
 recognition by securing a research grant of PKR 3.5 Million from the Higher Education Commission's National Research Program
 for Universities.

Freelance Deep Learning Engineer

Nov 2020 — Mar 2021

UpWork & Freelancer

Remote

- Developed an image captioning algorithm for image retrieval by leveraging natural language descriptions associated with images.
- Designed and developed a GAN model specifically tailored for the detection of COVID-19 in CT scans.
- Developed a face recognition model using a custom developed CNN.
- Utilized SHAP and LIME for developing interpretable image classification models.

Research Assistant (Deep Learning)

Jan 2020 - Oct 2020

Bioinformatics Research Lab, UET

Lahore, Pakistan

- Worked with Prof. Dr. Muhammad Usman Ghani Khan for detection of rare and lethal Acral Lentiginous Melanoma using dermoscopic images.
- Designed and implemented a specialized CNN architecture to develop an effective detection system for acral melanoma.
- Actively participated in Plant Disease Detection projects, leveraging deep learning and leaf image datasets.

Computer Vision Engineer

Aug 2019 — Dec 2019

Wizdojo Technologies

Lahore, Pakistan

- Developed a vehicle registration plate detection system using Mask R-CNN and Faster-RCNN.
- Collected and annotated data from live surveillance cameras and trained a Mask RCNN model to detect and segment the vehicle registration plate.
- Designed a pipeline for extracting text from segmented licese plate using Tesseract OCR.
- Developed a static website using HTML/Boostrcap/CSS for the company's product FuelAI.

EDUCATION

MS Computer Science Sep 2018 — Dec 2020

University of Engineering and Technology Lahore, Pakistan | Top 10%

CGPA 3.78/4.00

• Thesis: Detection and Prediction of Acral Lentiginous Melanoma in Dermoscopic Images using Deep Learning

BS Information Technology

Oct 2014 — May 2018

University of Sargodha, Sargodha, Pakistan | Gold Medalist

CGPA: 3.63/4.00

• FYP: Energy Optimized Smart Surveillance System using a Raspberry Pi and Pi Camera

CERTIFICATIONS

Python 3 Programming Specialization by University of Michigan
 Deep Learning Specialization by deeplearning.ai
 Mathematics for Machine Learning by Imperial College London
 Al for Medical Diagnosis by deeplearning.ai
 June 2020

REFERENCES

· Prof. Dr. Muhammad Usman Ghani Khan

Professor & Chairman Department of Computer Science, UET Lahore, Pakistan

Email: usman.ghani@uet.edu.pk

· Dr. Sadaf Hina

Lecturer, Department of Computer Science, University of Salford, the UK

Email: s.hina@salford.ac.uk

Muaaz Hafiz

Project Manager, SDSol Technologies

Email: muaaz@sdsol.com